<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two very lamentable relations the one, the grieuances for religion, of those of Stiria, Carinthia, and Crayne, vnder Ferdinand then Duke of Gratz, now Emperour. The other, the now present most humble supplication, of certayne of the states of lower Austria, vnto the said Emperour. Wherein is shewed the most terrible, inhumane, and barbarian tyrannies, committed by the Emperours souldiers, specially the Casockes and Wallons, in the said countrie. Done out of the Dutch, and printed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854996</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854996</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10593)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1556:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two very lamentable relations the one, the grieuances for religion, of those of Stiria, Carinthia, and Crayne, vnder Ferdinand then Duke of Gratz, now Emperour. The other, the now present most humble supplication, of certayne of the states of lower Austria, vnto the said Emperour. Wherein is shewed the most terrible, inhumane, and barbarian tyrannies, committed by the Emperours souldiers, specially the Casockes and Wallons, in the said countrie. Done out of the Dutch, and printed.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Holland? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C²  (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferdinand --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  1618-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two very lamentable Relations:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The one,</hi> The grieuance for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of thoſe of <hi>Stiria, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinthia,</hi> and <hi>Crayne,</hi> vnder FERD<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ND <hi>then Duke of Gratz, now</hi> Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other,</hi> The now preſent moſt humble S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, of certayne of the States of <hi>lower Auſtria, vnto the ſaid</hi> Emperour.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewed the moſt terrible, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, <hi>and barbarian tyrannies, committed by</hi> the Emperours Souldiers, ſpecially the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſockes</hi> and <hi>Wallons,</hi> in the ſaid Countrie.</p>
            <p>Done out of the Dutch, and Printed.</p>
            <p>1620.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:2"/>
            <head>The grieuances for Religion of thoſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Prouinces of <hi>Stiria, Carinthia,</hi> and <hi>Crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> not onely in their Bodies outwardly, but alſo in their Conſciences inwardly, for the Teſtimonie of the true Goſpell; moſt cruelly perſecuted, by the enemies of the Truth, and their Commiſſaries: Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der FERDINAND, now Emperour, then Duke of <hi>Gratz</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO declare to the World the hourely and minutely griefe of Conſcience and grieuances for the Religion which wee haue had, were almoſt impoſſible and alſo vnneceſſary, ſince it is, alas, too well knowne to this Land, to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and to a great part of the World; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe we will rehearſe a few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, by priuiledge, and good will of the illuſtrious Arch-Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> of famous memory, our gracious Lord and Prince, was granted to the profeſſors of the Goſpell, many ſpeciall Miniſters in principall Townes as in <hi>Gratz, Indenburgk, Clagenfourt,</hi> and <hi>Labach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Item,</hi> their Colledges and free Schooles of learning, for inſtructing Noblemens, and others Children, were admitted and granted them, in the foreſaid Townes of <hi>Gratz, Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genfourt,</hi> and <hi>Labach,</hi> all which priuiledges are moſt violently taken from them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:20466:3"/>3. <hi>Item,</hi> in the Countrey of <hi>Stiria,</hi> were many Cathedrall and other Pariſh Churches alſo violently taken from them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Alſo many priuiledged Churches, pulled downe, and blowne vp with Gunpowder.</p>
            <p n="5">5. One hundred Preachers and Miniſters commanded vpon paine of death to depart the prouince of <hi>Stiria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. A great many more Schoole-maſters, and Teachers of the Youth, moſt pittifully baniſhed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> many Church-yards, and reſting places for the dead bodyes of the faithfull, being walled and paled about, were moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly pulled downe, and made leuell with the ground.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The bodies of the faithfull digged vp, and giuen to be deuoured by Dogs and Hogs; as alſo the Coffins taken and ſet by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſide, ſome burnt with fire; a worke both barbarous and inhumane.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Alſo vpon the buriall places of the faithfull, were erected Gibets and places for execution of malefactors. Alſo vpon thoſe places where Proteſtant Churches ſtood, or where the Pulpit ſtood, or the Font-ſtone, were erected alwaies moſt filthy ſpectacles moſt vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to behold.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> many thouſand of godly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious bookes, among which were many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb facs="tcp:20466:3"/> Bibles, the witneſſes of Gods moſt holy Word, vtterly burnt with fire.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Moreouer, (a griefe aboue all griefes) many thouſands that profeſſed the Goſpell, were moſt cruelly and ſhamefully tormented and tortured, and by the ſame torments com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled ſhamefully, to denie and renounce the truth of Chriſts Euangell.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Compelling thoſe of the Religion to ſweare vpon their ſaluation neuer to renounce that damnable Popiſh Idolatrie, the which they were now forced to by torments.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The poore diſtreſſed people, were alſo compelled to their extreame coſt and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to vphold and maintaine a ſtrong gard of Souldiers, for thoſe cruell Commiſſaries owne obedient <hi>mancipia</hi> and <hi>eùotoria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The conſtant Confeſſors and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſts moſt holy Word and Goſpell, together with their Wiues, and innocent Babes, were moſt cruelly compelled to leaue their dwellings and habitations (whether it were in Cities, Townes, or Villages) at the pleaſure of thoſe barbarous Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries; and the longeſt terme of their abode was, ſix weekes and three dayes, ſometimes but eight dayes, and ſometimes they muſt be gonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sun-ſetting, and ſometimes in the coldeſt time of Winter, in Froſt and Snow: although it be manifeſt by the peace of Religion, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:20466:4"/> in the yeere of God 1555. (as appeares by the <hi>Formalia</hi>) that all Subiects or Tenants vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Prince, or Noble-man, who were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for Religion, might freely chooſe the time of their departure out of the Countrie.</p>
            <p n="15">15. They were not admitted time and lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to make ſale of their Lands and Goods, but (as may appeare by that cruell <hi>Edict ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialis</hi>) they were conſtrained ſhamefully to ſell them, to their vnſpeakeable loſſe, yea, and ſometimes compelled to giue them; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that it moſt manifeſtly appeares alſo, by the foreſaid peace of Religion, that there ſhould be no compulſion, in ſelling or giuing of Goods or Lands, excepting only, in <hi>amore Chriſtianae Religionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if they did ſell their Goods or Lands, they were compelled to giue the tenth Penny thereof, as by way of taxation; alledging that in Electorall Princes and States Lands of the Empire they did the like. But, as it appeares plainely by the aforeſaid peace of Religion, it is ſaid, thoſe Countries ſhall pay the tenth Penny, who formerly did doe the ſame; but theſe our Countries haue euer beene free of thoſe taxations. We omit to remember that thoſe Iewes who were iuſtly expelled not long ſince, were freely pardoned this taxation.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Notwithſtanding, thoſe Iewes were bound by bond, to pay the tenth Penny, at
<pb facs="tcp:20466:4"/> their departure out of the Land <hi>per modum Compenſationis;</hi> but thoſe poore Chriſtian Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles muſt be baniſhed &amp; troubled, and forced not only to quit their Countrey, Friends, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance &amp; acquaintance; not only debarred the fruits of their labours, but alſo muſt be bereft of that little money appointed for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, in this their wofull baniſhment.</p>
            <p n="17">17. And this was not a baniſhment with moderation to thoſe deuout and moſt faithfull Chriſtians and our beloued Patriots, but they were exiled vnder paine of death neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. A baniſhment moſt infamous and moſt lamentable, that a man muſt bee conſtrained neuer to returne to the place of his natiuitie, there, where ſo many yeeres he had dwelt with honor and reſpect; there where are the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of his dead predeceſſors. Although it be expreſly ſet downe in the often ſpoken of peace of Religion, that it ſhall not be preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall for any man, freely to viſite his Countrie, and friends, from whom hee is baniſhed for Religion.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Alſo the Noble-men, and others of thoſe Prouinces being Proteſtants, were not exempted this infamy, but were put by their hereditary offices of State, onely becauſe they were of the Religion; and others were placed in their offices, being men of no qualitie or merit, and only becauſe they were of Romiſh
<pb facs="tcp:20466:5"/> Religion. Our Proteſtant Noble-men, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hindred from being Adminiſtrators, or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quutors to their friends or their children, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoug they deale neuer ſo faithfully: Which ſhewes moſt plainely, that theſe wrongs done vnto them, was not for the inſufficiencie of their perſons, births, or qualities, but only becauſe they were Proteſtants.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Alſo the Noble-men and Gentrie of thoſe Prouinces being Proteſtants, were moſt grieuouſly taxed and cauſed to pay great and grieuous ſummes of money, ouer &amp; aboue the tenth penny; notwithſtanding that they had quitted their Churches, Schooles, Preachers, and Schoole-maſters: yea, euen thoſe that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would ſometimes goe out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey for deuotion, to heare a Sermon, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, were conſtrained to pay the tenth penny, being out of his Highneſſe Countries; although it be manifeſt <hi>de iure,</hi> that <hi>nemo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra territorium ſuum</hi> can puniſh any man. All theſe iniuries are directly againſt his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (now Emperour) owne Edict, giuen to thoſe of the Religion the laſt of Aprill, 1599.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Theſe great and grieuous troubles and tyrannicall vexations, which wee haue beene and are plagued withall, were not ſo much to be pittied, if there were any hope of our eaſe, or reliefe. But alas! the vnmercifull anſwer and reſolution of his Highneſſe (now
<pb facs="tcp:20466:5"/> Emperour) giuen to the Proteſtants the eighth of December 1609. which was plainely told thoſe of the religion, That he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yeeld to their demandes, and that hee would continue in this his reſolution euen till his graue; and that before he would yeeld for any of the leaſt of their demands, concerning their Religion, he would rather aduenture the loſſe of all that euer he had of God, and with a white Staffe, goe barefooted out of all his Countries. Alſo his Highneſſe (now Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) did threaten mightily the Proteſtant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, vowing that he would be reuenged on them, for ſeeking any tolleration; alleadging that it was againſt his princely Authoritie.</p>
            <p n="21">21. To conclude, this laſt is the worſt of all, that his Highneſſe (now Emperor) will not heare his Nobility &amp; Gentry, nor one of thoſe of the Religion, but he oftentimes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded them vpon paine of their liues to keepe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſilence: as in Anno 1598. the thirtyeth of September; the fifth of May 1599. the fifth of March 1601. and this laſt time, the eighth of December 1609. Alſo it is moſt manifeſt in that Edict, in the yeere 1599. hee abſolutely forbids vnder the paine of death, that no man of what degree or qualitie whatſoeuer, ſhould entertaine any Preacher or Miniſter of the Goſpell; vowing alſo that hee will not heare any more of their grieuances: Which is, <hi>dura
<pb facs="tcp:20466:6"/> &amp; acerbavox regnantis, non velle audire &amp; ſcripta accipere, contrà quàm Vetula illa obijciebat Regi Macedonum</hi> Philippo <hi>audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam recuſanti: Si non vis audire, noli er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Regnare.</hi> The abuſes in Religion is no new thing, eſpecially of the ſpirituall ſort, but if the Spiritualitie did commit any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or gaue any euill example, it was to be ſeene into by their temporall Princes and Lords, as we haue a fine example in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Stiria</hi> (fol. 81,) in the yeere of God 1518. When Doctor <hi>Luther</hi> had gotten the vpper hand, he gaue in a long <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Complaints and abuſes of the Clergie to the Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> complayning of the abuſes of their Benefices, their neglect of Gods Seruice, the inſolencies commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Dioceſſe, the careleſneſſe of their ſaluation, of the euill gouerning of Church liuings, and of the too many idle perſons, that were maintained to the heauie burthen of the Countrey, as ſundry ſorts of <hi>Abbots, Canonicats, Prebendes, Commendats,</hi> and many others: his Imperiall Maieſtie graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly did promiſe a redreſſe, giuing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to all Dukes and Lords, to ſee a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. But at this time there is greater cauſe of redreſſe of abuſes, ſince it is to bee plainely ſeene, that wickedneſſe hath gotten
<pb facs="tcp:20466:6"/> the vpper hand, and alas! there is no hope of helpe, or redreſſe.</p>
            <p>If this Prince deales ſo hardly with his owne, much more cruelty is to be looked for at his hands, if he can haue the vpper hand of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:7"/>
            <head>The moſt humble Supplication of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the States of lower <hi>Auſtria</hi> made vnto the Emperour: Wherein is ſhewed the moſt terrible, inhumane, and barbarian tyrannyes, committed by the Emperours Souldiers, by the <hi>Caſockes</hi> and <hi>Wallons</hi> in the ſaid Countrie.</head>
            <p>MOſt gracious Prince, the vnſpeakeable ſpoyling, deſtruction, miſerie, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, calamitie, and ſubiection of theſe countries, wrought and effected by the accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Coſackes and others your Maieſties Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers brought into the ſame, together with the robbings, murtherings, ſackings, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, maſſacrings, and other barbarian cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties vſed and committed therein, mooueth and prouoketh vs in the name and behalfe of our principall Lords &amp; the whole Countrey, to take and haue our recourſe, next vnto God, to your Emperiall Maieſtie, with ſighes and teares to renew our former complaints. In regard that the ſame (in the leaſt degree) are not yet redreſſed, neither hath your Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſty, nor you Generals granted any meſſage, nor Mandate in writing for their ſafe conducts; and to obtayne ſome reliefe therein for your poore ſubiects. For although your Maieſty hath heretofore oftentimes beene certified and aduiſed, how and in what manner
<pb facs="tcp:20466:8"/> the Countrie in generall is ſpoyled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, both the Gentil-men and Commons rob'd and ranſackt, ſome of the Peſants kild, and ſome of them driuen from houſe &amp; home into the Woods, and Mountaynes; Vines and earable Lands ſpoyled and laid waſte, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ſet aſide; vertue, modeſtie, honeſtie, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, law and right hindred and neglected, and an innumerable company of ſinnes, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and horrible actions are daily committed, and cruelly exerciſed by the Souldiers. Your Maieſtie hauing moſt graciouſly granted and promiſed, to take ſpeedy order for the redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and preuention thereof; and to that end vouchſafed your Gracious Commiſſion to the Generall of your army, for the ceaſing and ſtay of the ſame: being compelled thereunto by meere neceſſitie and force, your poore and humble Subiects are againe vnited to renew their ſaid complaints, and to let your Maieſty know, that the ſaid inſolencies are not by any meanes ceaſed, nor yet leſſened, but rather from day to day, and continually, are ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and more and more encreaſed and wax ſtronger, yea, and in ſuch barbarian, vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and inhumane manner, that we are aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and abaſhed to thinke thereon, and in a manner haue a deteſtation to name them to certifie your Maieſty thereof. Therefore ſith the vnruly Souldiers, ſpecially the Coſackes,
<pb facs="tcp:20466:8"/> ſtil perſiſt in ſuch their ſtrange, feareful, and deteſtable actions, and that there is no forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance nor diſtaſte thereof in any ſort, as alſo being certified, that the ſame is to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and practiſed by others of your Maieſties troops. Wee, being vpon more then a ſure ground, for that we are certainely perſwaded in our conſciences, that it cannot be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before God, together with the States, whoſe Officers are reſpectiuely to maintaine the Countrie, moued with no ſmall griefe and inward vexation of mind to behold the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate of the country-people, &amp; being go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours and fathers of the ſame, (as the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of euery Gouuernor and Stateſ-man bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him) moſt heartily and earneſtly deſiring and wiſhing to ſee a remedie therein. Hoping that your Imperiall Maieſtie, will not in any wiſe be offended, nor take it in euill part, that in ſome ſort we make the ſame knowne vnto your Maieſty, only to the end, that your ſaid Maieſty, as a Chriſtian Potentate, and a moſt gracious Prince of the houſe of Auſtria, may the rather with all ſpeede ſeeke to remedy, and take ayde for the diuerting of theſe great, moſt enorme, and miſchieuous proceedings.</p>
            <p>So it is, and it pleaſed your Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, that for as much, as the <hi>Wallons,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrange Souldiers, brought into this Country, ceaſe not continually, to make a common practiſe to waſte, ſpoyle, burne, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:20466:9"/> and maſſacre the Countrie and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons thereof, whereby there is not any feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnſpeakeable, and inhumane action what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, which they, and other of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſouldiers with al cruelty, and bloud-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe, haue not effected, exerciſed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; ſparing not to burne whole Villages, Hamlets, and Market-townes, and in them Store-houſes for the prouiſion of Widdowes and Orphans, (among the which we alſo that are Ambaſſadors, and haue a ſpeciall protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your Maieſty for our defence againſt all oppreſſions, are not ſpared) ſeiſed vpon, ſpoyled, and burnt their Caſtles, houſes, and their prouiſion for their houſes, being taken from them; the poore ſubiects that are employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about neceſſary defences, cannot get a bit of bread to relieue themſelues withall, but are conſtrained to ſtarue and die for hunger. Boys and Women being fearefully violated &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed, are carried priſoners away, both young and old men and women, moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly and terribly martired, torterd, preſt, their fleſh pinſht, and pulled from their bodies with burning tonges, hangd vp by the necks, hands, feete, and their priuy-members; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, gentlewomen, and young wenches vnder yeeres rauiſhed till they die, women great with child, layd ſo long vpon the fire, vntill which time as that men may ſee the fruit in their bodies, and ſo both mother and child
<pb facs="tcp:20466:9"/> die together, old and young, high and low ſtates, ſpirituall and temporal perſons, without any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, oppreſſed, and many thouſands of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent people fearefully murthered. Some in their caſtles (and yet ſuch as haue deſerued wel at your Maieſties and the houſe of Auſtrias hands, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old &amp; good friends to the ſame) notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Letters Pattents of aſſurance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, (becauſe they profeſſe the Lutheran Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) pitifully murthered. Some of them with their wiues and children being brought forth in their ſhirts and ſmocks, and wholly bereft of all reliefe, and ſuch as flie out into the fields, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred there to be free from their cruelties, but run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after them, haue beene moſt pitifully ſlaine, and hewed to peeces. And many men of great account haue beene glad to take Paſports from their owne ſeruants, with many other ſuch like vnſpeakeable and inhumane inſolencies, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and cruel actions that are practiſed; which although, now (as loth to make them knowne vnto your Maieſty) we forbeare to write it as much as in conſcience we can, and wil anſwere for the ſame before God, we wil hereafter not ſpare to declare.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſith we know, that your Maieſty takes no pleaſure in theſe feareful and horrible exceſſes, and intolerable abuſes, &amp; much more in reſpect of your Chriſtian charitie &amp; Princely minde, cannot but conceiue a great diſliking thereof; and that it is to bee feared, that your Maieſty hath not yet, or may for a long time refraine from reſoluing vpon
<pb facs="tcp:20466:10"/> an anſwer to be made, &amp; order to be taken touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe our obedient &amp; humble ſupplications, and therefore the ſame wil haue no end nor be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, whereby the whole Country will bee in danger to bee laid waſte, the Lords and ſubiects of the ſame brought and reduced into extreme miſerie and affliction, to the great preiudice, not only of your Maieſty, but alſo of the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and worthy houſe of Auſtria, and an vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerable damage vnto the Empire. Wee moſt humbly, once againe beſeech your Maieſty, in the name of our principall States, for the mercy of God, in the bleeding wounds of our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that you would be pleaſed, according to your naturall commendable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian, and Imperiall clemencie, to haue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon the neceſſitie, miſerie, and pitifull eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of your faithfull States, Subiects, and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, whereby your Maieſty ſhall not only bee a furtherance to your owne deſiring of peace, quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and proſperitie, and procure your moſt gracious ſatisfaction, but alſo obtayne immortall commendation of all poſteritie. Which your faithfull and bounden ſubiects wil endeuour with all dutie and obedience to deſerue at your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties gracious hands, wherewith we referre our ſelues to your moſt Princely pleaſure and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The true neather Auſtrian Euangelicall Committees and Ambaſſadours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20466:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
